#	Text	JP	EN	FR	IT	DE	ES
0	 						
1	 						
2	 						
3	ワールドマップや、運命の書に	"ワールドマップや、運命の書に
重なった状態で、パーティメン
バーを入れ替えられます。"	"Lets you change party members on the 
world map or when standing in reach of 
Records of Fate."	"Permet de modifier les membres de
l'équipe sur la carte du monde ou
à proximité de Voix du Sort."	"Ti permette di cambiare i membri del 
gruppo sulla mappa del mondo o quando 
sei nelle vicinanze delle Registrazioni del 
Fato."	"Lässt dich auf der Weltkarte und in der 
Nähe von Schicksalsspeichern 
Gruppenmitglieder austauschen."	"Permite cambiar de miembros de grupo 
en el mapamundi o al tocar registros del 
hado."
4	重なった状態で、パーティメン						
5	バーを入れ替えられます。						
6	キキの父親が、１０年前に魚捕	"キキの父親が、１０年前に魚捕
りになろうと決めたときに作っ
たライオンザメの歯のお守り。"	"An amulet Kiki's father made from a lion 
shark tooth ten years ago, when he 
decided to be a fisherman."	"Amulette que le père de Kiki fabriqua à 
partir d'une dent de requin-lion il y a 10 
ans, lorsqu'il décida de devenir pêcheur."	"Un amuleto che il padre di Kiki ricavò 
da un dente di squalo-leone, circa dieci 
anni fa, quando decise di diventare 
un pescatore."	"Diesen Glücksbringer bastelte Kikis Vater 
vor zehn Jahren, als er beschloss, Fischer 
zu werden."	"Amuleto que el padre de Kika talló con 
el diente de un escualo hace diez años, 
cuando decidió hacerse pescador."
7	りになろうと決めたときに作っ						
8	たライオンザメの歯のお守り。						
9	星色の小さなお守り。	星色の小さなお守り。	"A small, star-colored talisman."	Petit talisman coloré en forme d'étoile.	"Questo piccolo talismano ha il colore 
delle stelle."	"Kleiner, sternförmiger Talisman."	"Pequeño talismán del color de las 
estrellas."
10	　						
11	　						
12	この鈴の音色に沼の植物が反応	"この鈴の音色に沼の植物が反応
し、直接触れなくとも、くねっ
と曲がって道ができるらしい。"	"Marsh plants react to the sound of this 
bell, bending to open the way without 
you having to touch them."	"Les plantes des marais réagissent au bruit 
de ce grelot et se couchent pour ouvrir la 
voie sans que vous ayez à les toucher."	"Le piante delle paludi reagiscono al 
suono di questa campanella, e si piegano 
aprendo la via senza che tu debba 
toccarle."	"Sumpfpflanzen weichen angeblich vor dem 
Klang dieser Glocke zurück und geben so 
den Weg frei."	"Su tañido hace que las plantas del marjal 
abran paso sin tener siquiera que 
tocarlas."
13	し、直接触れなくとも、くねっ						
14	と曲がって道ができるらしい。						
15	コレ、ピパ族ニ伝ワル不思議ナ	"コレ、ピパ族ニ伝ワル不思議ナ
笛ナンダナ。ロザリー、コレデ
手ナズケラレルンダナ。"	"A mysterious flute handed down in the 
Beeba tribe. It allows you to tame the 
wildest of Wingapedes!"	"Flûte mystérieuse qui se transmet au sein 
de la tribu des Bibas. Elle vous permet de 
dompter les aéroptères les plus sauvages."	"Un misterioso strumento musicale 
tramandato da generazioni nella tribù dei 
Beeba. Può domare anche il più selvaggio 
dei Pedalat!"	"Dieser Schatz der Biba vermag mit seinem 
Klang selbst die wildeste Flugschrecke zu 
besänftigen."	"Misteriosa flauta de la tribu de los 
babatracios que puede domar a la 
aeromantis más fiera."
16	笛ナンダナ。ロザリー、コレデ						
17	手ナズケラレルンダナ。						
18	ガライが使っていた伝説の龍の	"ガライが使っていた伝説の龍の
剣。魔剣グランドリオンの邪気
を払うことができる唯一の剣。"	"The legendary dragon sword Garai once 
wielded. It is the only sword able to beat 
Masamune's evil power."	"Légendaire épée dragon que Garaï 
brandit autrefois. C'est la seule arme à 
rivaliser avec le pouvoir maléfique de 
Masamune."	"La leggendaria spada del drago 
impugnata da Garai. È l'unica lama in 
grado di sconfiggere il malvagio potere 
della Masamune."	"Einzig Garais legendäres Drachenschwert 
kann die böse Macht des Grandelion 
bezwingen."	"Legendaria espada dragón de Garai. 
Es la única arma capaz de vencer el poder 
maligno de la Masamune."
19	剣。魔剣グランドリオンの邪気						
20	を払うことができる唯一の剣。						
21	ルッカが作った、火を消すお供	"ルッカが作った、火を消すお供
に最適な急速冷凍銃。
子供はさわっちゃダメらしい。"	"A quick-freeze gun Lucca made so 
babysitters could fight fires. 
=Keep out of reach of children!="	"Arme de gel inventée par Lucca pour que 
les nounous puissent éteindre les 
incendies. 
Ne pas laisser à la portée des enfants !"	"Lucca ha inventato quest'arma a 
congelamento rapido per permettere alle 
baby-sitter di spegnere gli incendi. 
Tenere lontana dalla portata dei bambini!"	"Luccas Erfindung für Babysitter, die damit 
im Ernstfall per Knopfdruck Feuer löschen 
können."	"Pistola refrigerante que fabricó Lucca 
para evitar incendios domésticos. 
Solo apta para adultos."
22	に最適な急速冷凍銃。						
23	子供はさわっちゃダメらしい。						
24	水龍より授かった、にえたぎる	"水龍より授かった、にえたぎる
マグマをも凍てつかせる冷たい
息吹。"	"The cold breath of the Water Dragon has 
the power to freeze even piping-hot 
magma."	"Le souffle glacé du Dragon de l'eau peut 
même geler le magma."	"Il respiro ghiacciato del Drago dell'Acqua 
può congelare anche il magma 
incandescente."	"Der frostige Atem des Eisdrachen lässt 
sogar brodelnde Lava gefrieren."	"Frío aliento del Dragón de Agua que 
puede congelar hasta la lava."
25	マグマをも凍てつかせる冷たい						
26	息吹。						
27	ヘケランのスネ骨。スープの	"ヘケランのスネ骨。スープの
ダシを取ったり、シチューに
するとウマイ。"	"The leg bone of a wild Heckran. 
Perfect for making stock to be used in 
soups and stews!"	"Fémur d'un héclan sauvage. Il est tout 
indiqué pour préparer du bouillon pour 
les soupes et les ragoûts."	"Un osso della gamba di un Heckran 
selvatico. È perfetto per preparare dadi 
per insaporire il brodo o lo stufato!"	"Der Beinknochen eines wilden Hekran. 
Gibt Suppen und Eintöpfen ein 
unvergleichliches Aroma!"	"Fémur de un heclan salvaje. 
¡Perfecto para hacer un buen caldo!"
28	ダシを取ったり、シチューに						
29	するとウマイ。						
30	溺れ谷にしか咲かない	"溺れ谷にしか咲かない
美しい青い花。"	"A blue blossom that only blooms in the 
Fossil Valley."	"Fleur bleue qui ne pousse que dans la 
vallée des Fossiles."	"Un fiore blu che sboccia solo nella Valle 
dei Fossili."	"Eine blaue Blume, die nur in der 
Fossilienschlucht wächst."	Flor azul que solo crece en Valle Fósil.
31	美しい青い花。						
32	　						
33	溺れ谷で拾った巨大な卵。	"溺れ谷で拾った巨大な卵。
何の卵かは不明。"	"A huge egg found in the Fossil Valley. 
What kind of egg it is remains unknown!"	"Gros œuf découvert dans la vallée des 
Fossiles. 
Nul ne sait quel animal l'a pondu!"	"Un gigantesco uovo trovato nella Valle 
dei Fossili. Non si sa quale creatura lo 
abbia deposto."	"Ein Ei aus der Fossilienschlucht. 
Groß ist es. Was darin schlummert, 
weiß niemand."	"Enorme huevo encontrado en Valle Fósil. 
¡Quién sabe lo que saldrá de dentro!"
34	何の卵かは不明。						
35	　						
36	道化師メイクの頭がい骨。	"道化師メイクの頭がい骨。
失われた記憶と体を探している
らしい。見た目より重い。"	"A human skull painted with clown's 
makeup. It says it is searching for its 
body and lost memories."	"Crâne humain maquillé comme un clown. 
Il dit chercher son corps et ses souvenirs 
perdus."	"Un teschio umano truccato da clown. 
Dice che sta cercando il suo corpo e i 
suoi ricordi perduti."	"Ein als Clown geschminkter Schädel. 
Behauptet, er suche seinen Körper und 
seine verlorenen Erinnerungen."	"Cráneo humano pintado con maquillaje 
de payaso. Afirma estar buscando su 
cuerpo y sus recuerdos."
37	失われた記憶と体を探している						
38	らしい。見た目より重い。						
39	生前は、おばあさんの教育が良	"生前は、おばあさんの教育が良
かったせいか、とても姿勢の良
い背筋だったようだ。"	"A spine with good posture that must have 
come from a grandma's loving training in 
its former life."	"Colonne vertébrale dont la rectitude a dû 
découler, de son vivant, d'une éducation 
stricte mais d'un autre âge."	"Questa spina dorsale dalla postura 
perfetta dev'essere appartenuta a una 
nonna che amava fare esercizio fisico."	"Ein formschönes Rückgrat. Zeugnis 
stetiger, liebevoller Ermahnungen der 
Oma seines früheren Besitzers."	"Columna vertebral tratada con la misma 
rectitud de la que presume. 
¡100 % libre de chepas!"
40	かったせいか、とても姿勢の良						
41	い背筋だったようだ。						
42	生前は、玉乗りから空中ブラン	"生前は、玉乗りから空中ブラン
コまで、何でもこなすガッチリ
した体格だったようだ。"	"The owner must have done various 
gymnastics and aerobatics in order to 
build a body this solid."	"Son propriétaire devait suivre un 
entraînement physique quotidien pour 
avoir un corps si solide."	"Il possessore di queste parti anatomiche 
deve aver fatto molta ginnastica per 
costruire un corpo tanto robusto..."	"Der Besitzer dieses Vorzeigebrustkorbs 
muss zu Lebzeiten ganz schön fit gewesen 
sein."	"Costillas de muy buen ver propias de 
algún acróbata duro de roer."
43	コまで、何でもこなすガッチリ						
44	した体格だったようだ。						
45	生前は、しっかりした腰付き	"生前は、しっかりした腰付き
だったようだ。何事もコシが
大事。"	"Even from the pelvis, you can see this 
person had good posture. 
It is important to have good posture!"	"Il suffit de voir ce bassin pour affirmer 
que cette personne se tenait droite. 
C'est important de se tenir droit !"	"Quest'osso pelvico mostra chiaramente 
che il suo possessore aveva un'ottima 
postura. Avere un'ottima postura è 
molto importante!"	"Der makellose Beckenknochen lässt auf 
eherne Disziplin und Haltung seines 
Besitzers schließen."	"¡Nada como una pelvis robusta para 
mover bien el esqueleto!"
46	だったようだ。何事もコシが						
47	大事。						
48	生前は、いつも何かに怒りを	"生前は、いつも何かに怒りを
持っていた。それは自分に対す
る怒りだったのかも知れない。"	"These shoulder blades obviously bore 
a lot of hatred. Perhaps the owner hated 
himself while alive..."	"Ces omoplates portaient un fardeau de 
haine. Leur propriétaire se détestait 
peut-être... de son vivant."	"Si vede subito che queste scapole hanno 
portato tanto odio. Forse il loro 
possessore odiava persino se stesso, 
quand'era vivo..."	"Diese Schultern zeugen von einer 
schweren Bürde des Hasses. 
Hasste der Besitzer sich gar selbst?"	"Se nota que estos omoplatos están 
cargados de rencor. Igual su dueño se 
odiaba a sí mismo en vida..."
49	持っていた。それは自分に対す						
50	る怒りだったのかも知れない。						
51	どれがどの骨だかはっきりしな	"どれがどの骨だかはっきりしな
い。適当にくっつけるしかない
ようだ。"	"It is impossible to tell which bone is 
which. You'll just have to try putting 
them in some kind of order."	"Il est impossible de reconnaître les 
différents os. Vous devrez essayer de les 
replacer dans un certain ordre."	"Non si riesce a distinguerle, a capire che 
ossa siano... L'unica cosa da fare è 
cercare di metterle in ordine."	"Schwer zu sagen, welcher dieser Knochen 
einst wo hingehörte ... Betrachte sie 
einfach als Puzzle!"	"Buen surtido de huesos imposibles de 
identificar. 
¡A ver quién es el listo que los arma!"
52	い。適当にくっつけるしかない						
53	ようだ。						
54	身に着けて植物を調べると、	"身に着けて植物を調べると、
植物の実がまとわりついてくる
効能があるらしい。"	"When worn, it has the power to make 
seeds and fruit cling to you upon 
examining plants."	"Portez-la pour que les graines et les fruits 
s'accrochent à vous lorsque vous examinez 
des plantes."	"Se lo indossi, ti fa attaccare addosso 
semi e frutti, quando esamini una pianta."	"Hat anscheinend einen anziehenden 
Effekt auf Früchte und Samen, wenn man 
Pflanzen untersucht."	"Este saquito puede hacer que las semillas 
y los frutos se te peguen como lapas."
55	植物の実がまとわりついてくる						
56	効能があるらしい。						
57	ガルディア地方でしか採れない	"ガルディア地方でしか採れない
貴重な珍味の、もけもけだけ…
に似ているきのこ。"	"An expensive delicacy found only in the 
Guardia region. It's sort of like 
truffles without the chocolate."	"Mets délicat qu'on ne trouve que dans la 
région de Gardia. Cela ressemble à 
des truffes au chocolat sans chocolat."	"Questa costosa prelibatezza si trova solo 
nella regione di Guardia. Ha il gusto del 
tartufo al cioccolato... ma senza il 
cioccolato."	"Wächst ausschließlich in Gardia. Eine 
teure Delikatesse. Wie Trüffel, 
nur ohne die Schokolade."	"Seta delicada que solo crece en 
la región de Gardia. A simple 
vista, parece comestible..."
58	貴重な珍味の、もけもけだけ…						
59	に似ているきのこ。						
60	蛇骨館本館入り口の鍵。龍舎の	"蛇骨館本館入り口の鍵。龍舎の
じいさんから拝借中。蛇骨の紋
章が刻まれている。"	"The key to the front door of Viper Manor 
borrowed from the old stableman. 
Bears Viper's insignia."	"Clef de l'entrée principale du manoir 
Ophide empruntée à un vieux valet 
d'écurie. Elle porte les armes des Ophide."	"La chiave del portone principale di Castel 
Viper, che è stata prestata dal vecchio 
stalliere. Su di essa è impresso il simbolo 
di Viper."	"Gehört zur Eingangstür der Villa. 
Vom Bund des alten Stallmeisters. 
Vipers Wappen ziert die Reite."	"Llave de acceso a la Mansión de los 
Ofidios que te entregó el viejo mozo de 
cuadra. Con la insignia de los Ofidios."
61	じいさんから拝借中。蛇骨の紋						
62	章が刻まれている。						
63	ヒドラの体液から精製する解毒	"ヒドラの体液から精製する解毒
剤が、ヒドラの毒を中和する唯
一の方法。"	"Refined from the body fluids of a hydra, 
this liquid is the only known antidote for 
hydra poison."	"Réalisé à partir des fluides corporels 
filtrés d'une hydre, ce liquide est le seul 
antidote connu au poison de l'hydre."	"Ricavato dai fluidi corporei di un'Idra, 
questo liquido è l'unico antidoto 
conosciuto al veleno di quel pericoloso 
animale."	"Ein Trank aus dem Körpersaft einer 
Hydra. Einzig bekannter Wirkstoff gegen 
das Gift der Bestie."	"Bilis de hidra refinada. Es el único 
antídoto eficaz contra el veneno de estas 
criaturas."
64	剤が、ヒドラの毒を中和する唯						
65	一の方法。						
66	蛇骨館の地下室で拾った客間の	"蛇骨館の地下室で拾った客間の
鍵。ものぐさな兵士が隠してお
いたようだ。"	"A key to the parlor of Viper Manor that 
was found in the manor prison. 
Probably hidden by a lazy guard."	"Clef ouvrant le boudoir du manoir 
Ophide trouvée dans la prison du manoir. 
Elle avait probablement été cachée par 
un garde paresseux."	"La chiave del salotto di Castel Viper, 
trovata nella prigione del maniero. 
Probabilmente l'aveva nascosta lì una
guardia pigra."	"Öffnet die Tür des Salons in der 
Vipernvilla. Lag (nicht besonders gut 
versteckt) im Kerker."	"Llave de los aposentos de la Mansión de 
los Ofidios que yacía en los calabozos. 
¿Se le caería a un guarda?"
67	鍵。ものぐさな兵士が隠してお						
68	いたようだ。						
69	蛇骨館の地下牢を開くことがで	"蛇骨館の地下牢を開くことがで
きる鍵。"	"A key that opens the dungeon-like prison 
beneath Viper Manor."	"Clef ouvrant les cachots situés sous le 
manoir Ophide."	"La chiave che apre le labirintiche carceri 
che si trovano sotto Castel Viper."	"Gewährt Zugang zum Kerker unter der 
Vipernvilla."	"Llave de los calabozos que hay en el 
sótano de la Mansión de los Ofidios."
70	きる鍵。						
71	　						
72	伝説の秘宝の一つ。相手と精神	"伝説の秘宝の一つ。相手と精神
を入れ替えて体を乗っ取る事が
出来るなど不思議な力がある。"	"A legendary treasure that enables its 
possessor to switch bodies with someone 
else."	"Trésor légendaire permettant à son 
propriétaire d'échanger son corps avec 
quelqu'un d'autre."	"Questo tesoro leggendario permette a chi 
lo possiede di scambiare il proprio corpo 
con quello di qualcun altro."	"Der Besitzer dieses legendären Schatzes 
kann damit seine Seele in andere Körper 
transferieren."	"Tesoro legendario que permite a su 
portador intercambiar su cuerpo con 
el de otra persona."
73	を入れ替えて体を乗っ取る事が						
74	出来るなど不思議な力がある。						
75	天龍の島で天龍より授かった	"天龍の島で天龍より授かった
白龍神の秘宝。"	"A special treasure received from the 
White Dragon God at Sky Dragon Isle."	"Trésor spécial obtenu auprès du Dragon 
divin blanc à l'île du Dragon des cieux."	"Un tesoro speciale donato dal Divino 
Drago Bianco sull'Isola del Drago del 
Cielo."	"Ein besonderer Schatz, den dir der 
Himmelsdrache auf seiner Insel anvertraut 
hat."	"Tesoro especial otorgado por el dios 
dragón blanco en la Isla del Dragón 
Celestial."
76	白龍神の秘宝。						
77	　						
78	マブーレで黒龍より授かった	"マブーレで黒龍より授かった
黒龍神の秘宝。"	"A special treasure received from the 
Black Dragon God at Marbule."	"Trésor spécial obtenu auprès du Dragon 
divin noir à Marbule."	"Un tesoro speciale donato dal Divino 
Drago Nero a Marbule."	"Ein besonderer Schatz, den dir der 
Schwarze Drache in Marbule anvertraut 
hat."	"Tesoro especial otorgado por el dios 
dragón negro en Gneis."
79	黒龍神の秘宝。						
80	　						
81	死炎山で炎龍より授かった	"死炎山で炎龍より授かった
赤龍神の秘宝。"	"A special treasure received from the 
Red Dragon God at Mount Pyre."	"Trésor spécial obtenu auprès du Dragon 
divin rouge au mont de la Fournaise."	"Un tesoro speciale donato dal Divino 
Drago Rosso sul Monte Pyro."	"Ein besonderer Schatz, den dir der 
Feuerdrache auf dem Scheiterkogel 
anvertraut hat."	"Tesoro especial otorgado por el dios 
dragón escarlata en el Monte Ígneo."
82	赤龍神の秘宝。						
83	　						
84	水龍島で水龍より授かった	"水龍島で水龍より授かった
青龍神の秘宝。"	"A special treasure received from the 
Blue Dragon God at Water Dragon Isle."	"Trésor spécial obtenu auprès du Dragon 
divin bleu à l'île du Dragon de l'eau."	"Un tesoro speciale donato dal Divino 
Drago Blu sull'Isola del Drago dell'Acqua."	"Ein besonderer Schatz, den dir der 
Wasserdrache auf seiner Insel anvertraut 
hat."	"Tesoro especial otorgado por el dios 
dragón índigo en la Isla del Dragón de 
Agua."
85	青龍神の秘宝。						
86	　						
87	土龍の島で土龍より授かった	"土龍の島で土龍より授かった
黄龍神の秘宝。"	"A special treasure received from the 
Yellow Dragon God at Earth Dragon Isle."	"Trésor spécial obtenu auprès du Dragon 
divin jaune à l'île du Dragon de la terre."	"Un tesoro speciale donato dal Divino 
Drago Giallo sull'Isola del Drago della 
Terra."	"Ein besonderer Schatz, den dir der 
Erddrache auf seiner Insel anvertraut hat."	"Tesoro especial otorgado por el dios 
dragón dorado en la Isla del Dragón de 
Tierra."
88	黄龍神の秘宝。						
89	　						
90	世界のへそで緑龍より授かった	"世界のへそで緑龍より授かった
緑龍神の秘宝。"	"A special treasure received from the 
Green Dragon God at Gaea's Navel."	"Trésor spécial obtenu auprès du Dragon 
divin vert au havre de Gaïa."	"Un tesoro speciale donato dal Divino 
Drago Verde all'Ombelico di Gaea."	"Ein besonderer Schatz, den dir der 
Grüne Drache in Gaias Nabel anvertraut 
hat."	"Tesoro especial otorgado por el dios 
dragón esmeralda en el Ombligo de Gea."
91	緑龍神の秘宝。						
92	　						
93	人造人間植物改良種フィオに	"人造人間植物改良種フィオに
生命を与える事ができる。"	"A botanical energy that will give life to 
the NeoFio -- a man-made 
half-human, half-plant life-form."	"Énergie végétale qui donnera naissance à 
Néo Flor, une forme de vie mi-végétale 
mi-humaine créée par l'homme."	"Un'energia botanica che darà origine al 
Neo Fio, una forma di vita artificiale 
per metà umana e per metà vegetale."	"Botanische Energie. Soll dem halb 
menschlichen, halb pflanzlichen 
Wesen Neofio Leben einhauchen."	"Líquido biológico que sirve 
para dar vida a Neo Flora, 
la flor humanoide."
94	生命を与える事ができる。						
95	　						
96	トカゲのウロコで、ちゃらちゃ	"トカゲのウロコで、ちゃらちゃ
らしたネックレスを作るのが、
アルニ村の女子の間で流行中。"	"The colorful scale of a large lizard used 
to make the necklaces that are all the 
rage in Arni Village."	"Écaille colorée d'un grand lézard et 
utilisée pour fabriquer des colliers qui 
font fureur dans le village d'Arni."	"Questa scaglia colorata di una grande 
lucertola è usata per realizzare le collane 
che vanno tanto di moda nel villaggio 
di Arni."	"Schmuck aus diesen kunterbunten 
Echsenschuppen ist der letzte Schrei 
in Arni."	"Colorida escama de un lagarto grande con 
la que se hacen los collares tan de moda 
en la aldea de Arnia."
97	らしたネックレスを作るのが、						
98	アルニ村の女子の間で流行中。						
99	ひとでのようだが、秘密の力が	"ひとでのようだが、秘密の力
があるらしい。"	"It looks just like an ordinary starfish, 
but is said to have a secret power."	"Il ressemble à une étoile de mer 
ordinaire, mais il paraît qu'il détient un 
pouvoir caché."	"A prima vista sembra una normale stella 
marina, ma si dice che abbia un potere 
segreto."	"Sieht aus wie ein gewöhnlicher Seestern, 
soll aber über geheime Kräfte verfügen."	"Objeto con forma de estrella de mar que, 
al parecer, alberga un poder secreto."
100	あるらしい。						
101	　						
102	高度なテクノロジーによって作	"高度なテクノロジーによって作
られた、複製不可能なカード型
暗証キー。"	"A security pass built with futuristic 
technology that makes it impossible to 
duplicate."	"Pass de sécurité comportant une 
technologie futuriste qui empêche toute 
copie."	"Una chiave d'accesso realizzata con una 
tecnologia avanzatissima che ne rende 
impossibile la duplicazione."	"Diese Schlüsselkarte kann dank 
fortschrittlicher Technologie nicht 
vervielfältigt werden."	"Pase de seguridad que cuenta con los 
últimos avances tecnológicos y no se 
puede duplicar."
103	られた、複製不可能なカード型						
104	暗証キー。						
105	調査隊が使用する爆薬。	"調査隊が使用する爆薬。
危険物につき取り扱い注意。"	"An explosive device used by excavation 
teams.  =Handle with care!="	"Dispositif explosif utilisé par les 
équipes d'excavation. 
À manier avec précaution !"	"Un dispositivo esplosivo usato dalle 
squadre di scavo. Maneggiare con cura!"	"Nur zugelassen zum fachmännischen 
Einsatz durch Ausgrabungsteams! 
Bitte nicht fallen lassen!"	"Explosivo que usan los equipos de 
excavación. ¡Cuidado al manipularlo!"
106	危険物につき取り扱い注意。						
107	　						
108	龍の涙の破片。	龍の涙の破片。	A shard of the shattered Dragon Tear.	Éclat d'une Larme de dragon brisée.	"Un frammento della Lacrima di drago 
distrutta."	Ein Splitter der Drachenträne.	"Fragmento de la Lágrima de Dragón 
partida."
109	　						
110	　						
111	龍の涙の破片。	龍の涙の破片。	A shard of the shattered Dragon Tear.	Éclat d'une Larme de dragon brisée.	"Un frammento della Lacrima di drago 
distrutta."	Ein Splitter der Drachenträne.	"Fragmento de la Lágrima de Dragón 
partida."
112	　						
113	　						
114	このパスを使わないと、改札口	"このパスを使わないと、改札口
を通れない。"	"Without this pass, it is impossible to 
proceed through the station's turnstiles."	"Sans ce pass, il est impossible 
d'emprunter les tourniquets de la gare."	"Senza quest'oggetto è impossibile 
superare i tornelli della stazione."	"Ohne dieses Ticket kommt man nicht 
durch das Drehkreuz des Bahnhofs."	"Sin este pase, no podrás pasar por los 
tornos de la estación."
115	を通れない。						
116	　						
117	ロザリーニツイテタ種、ピパ族	"ロザリーニツイテタ種、ピパ族
ガ育テタ。一口喰エバロザリー
満足ナンダナ。"	"The fruit of an ancient plant that the 
Beeba tribe grows in order to tame 
Wingapedes."	"Fruit d'une plante séculaire que la tribu 
des Bibas cultive pour dompter les 
aéroptères."	"Il frutto di un'antica pianta che la tribù 
dei Beeba coltiva per domare i Pedalat."	"Wird von den Biba kultiviert und an wilde 
Flugschrecken verfüttert, um diese zu 
zähmen."	"Fruto de una planta ancestral que la tribu 
de los babatracios cultiva para domar 
aeromantis."
118	ガ育テタ。一口喰エバロザリー						
119	満足ナンダナ。						
120	きれいな細工の施された小さな	"きれいな細工の施された小さな
ペンダント。
ダリオの母の形見。"	"A beautiful, intricately made pendant 
that once belonged to Dario's mother."	"Joli pendentif ouvragé qui appartenait 
à la mère de Dario."	"Questo splendido ciondolo finemente 
lavorato apparteneva alla madre di Dario."	"Ein wunderschönes, fein gearbeitetes 
Medaillon, das einst Darios Mutter 
gehörte."	"Bonito colgante lleno de adornos que 
perteneció a la madre de Darío."
121	ペンダント。						
122	ダリオの母の形見。　						
123	片側がソケット状になっている	"片側がソケット状になっている
クランクハンドル。カジノでの
イカサマの証拠品。"	"A detachable crank-handle that serves as 
proof that the casino table is rigged."	"Manivelle amovible permettant de 
prouver que la table de jeu au casino est 
truquée."	"Questa manovella staccabile è la prova 
che il tavolo del casinò è truccato."	"Eine abschraubbare Handkurbel. Beweist, 
dass der Casinotisch manipuliert wurde."	"Manivela extraíble que demuestra que la 
mesa del casino está trucada."
124	クランクハンドル。カジノでの						
125	イカサマの証拠品。						
126	ガライの思い出とはどんなもの	"ガライの思い出とはどんなもの
だったのか、今となっては知る
由もない。"	"Just an old mirror. Why it is said to be 
a memento of Garai will never be known."	"Ce n'est qu'un vieux miroir. 
Nul ne sait en quoi il rappelle Garaï."	"È solo un vecchio specchio. Nessuno è in 
grado di dire per quale motivo sia 
considerato un ricordo di Garai..."	"Eigentlich nur ein alter Spiegel. Niemand 
weiß, warum er an Garai erinnern soll."	"Espejo sucio al que Garai parecía tener 
especial cariño, no se sabe muy bien por 
qué."
127	だったのか、今となっては知る						
128	由もない。						
129	実戦には使い物になりそうもな	"実戦には使い物になりそうもな
い。もっぱら装飾用として作られ
た、きれいな盾。"	"A beautiful shield made for completely 
ornamental purposes. 
Not of any use in a real battle."	"Très beau bouclier qui ne sert qu'à
être accroché et admiré. Il n'a
aucune utilité au combat."	"Questo meraviglioso scudo è stato 
realizzato a scopo unicamente 
ornamentale. 
Non ha alcuna utilità in battaglia."	"Ein schöner Schild. Nur für 
dekorative Zwecke gedacht, nicht 
für den Kampf."	"Bonito escudo fabricado con fines 
meramente decorativos. De poco 
serviría en un combate real."
130	い。もっぱら装飾用として作ら						
131	れた、きれいな盾。						
132	片方のツメが宝石のように青く	"片方のツメが宝石のように青く
輝く、シオマネキの作り物。潮
の満引をコントロールできる。"	"A sculpture of a fiddler crab with a claw 
that shines like a blue jewel. Said to be 
able to control the tides."	"Sculpture d'un crabe dont la pince brille 
d'un bleu intense. 
Il contrôlerait les flots."	"Questa scultura riproduce un granchio 
violinista con una chela che brilla come se 
fosse un gioiello azzurro. Si dice che 
possa controllare le maree."	"Eine der Scheren dieser Skulptur glänzt 
wie ein blauer Edelstein. 
Soll die Gezeiten steuern können."	"Figurita de un cangrejo con una pinza que 
brilla como si fuera una gema azul. 
Dicen que puede controlar las mareas."
133	輝く、シオマネキの作り物。潮						
134	の満引をコントロールできる。						
135	失われた第７の色属性を持つ、	"失われた第７の色属性を持つ、
究極のエレメント。"	"The ultimate, long-lost Element of the 
seventh color attribute."	"Dernier élément, disparu depuis une 
éternité, de l'attribut de la 7e couleur."	"L'Elemento dell'attributo del settimo 
colore, del quale si erano perse le tracce 
da lungo tempo."	"Das ultimative, verloren geglaubte 
Element des siebten Farbattributs."	"Elemento ancestral que alberga el 
séptimo atributo cromático."
136	究極のエレメント。						
137	　						
138	毒の沼地などに軽装で踏み込ん	"毒の沼地などに軽装で踏み込ん
だシロウトさん用に、調査隊が
予備で用意してあった耐毒服。"	"Poison-resistant clothing that an 
exploration party had spare to lend to 
amateur adventurers."	"Combinaison protégeant du poison 
qu'un groupe d'explorateurs trop bien 
équipé prêta à des aventuriers amateurs."	"Resistente al veleno, una squadra di 
esplorazione l'aveva in soprannumero, 
pronto per essere prestato ad avventurieri 
dilettanti."	"Giftresistente Kleidung. 
Gut, dass die Kundschafter Reserve 
für naive Abenteurer dabei hatten."	"Prenda resistente al veneno que unos 
exploradores tenían de sobra para los 
aventureros novatos."
139	だシロウトさん用に、調査隊が						
140	予備で用意してあった耐毒服。						
141	２つに割られた様な青い石が	"２つに割られた様な青い石が
はめ込まれたブローチ。"	"A brooch that has a blue stone, which 
appears to have been broken in two, 
set inside of it."	"Broche sertie d'une pierre bleue qui 
semble avoir été brisée en deux."	"In questa spilla è incastonata una pietra 
azzurra, che pare essere spezzata in due."	"Eine Brosche mit einem gesprungenen 
blauen Stein in der Mitte."	"Broche que lleva engastada en el centro 
la mitad de una gema azul aparentemente 
partida."
142	はめ込まれたブローチ。　						
143	　						
144	劇場の廃虚で拾った、演劇用の	"劇場の廃虚で拾った、演劇用の
小道具の剣。"	"A sword stage-prop found in the ruins 
of a theater."	"Accessoire de scène trouvé dans les 
ruines d'un théâtre."	"Questa spada di scena è stata trovata tra 
le rovine di un teatro."	"Eine Bühnenrequisite aus der Ruine eines 
Theaters."	"Espada de atrezo que estaba olvidada en 
las ruinas de un teatro."
145	小道具の剣。						
146	　						
147	龍の社に古来より伝わる伝統の	"龍の社に古来より伝わる伝統の
紋章。どこかで見たような紋様
だ。"	"A traditional crest passed down through 
the generations at the Dragon Shrine. 
The design looks familiar..."	"Blason traditionnel transmis de génération 
en génération au temple du Dragon. 
Son dessin rappelle quelque chose..."	"Uno stemma tramandato di generazione in 
generazione al Tempio del Drago. 
Ha un che di familiare..."	"Wird im Schrein des Drachen seit 
Generationen weitergegeben. 
Die Muster wirken vertraut..."	"Emblema que han custodiado los diversos 
líderes del Santuario del Dragón. 
Su diseño te suena de algo..."
148	紋章。どこかで見たような紋様						
149	だ。　						
150	タイトルもない、ちょっと安っ	"タイトルもない、ちょっと安っ
ぽい感じの手作りの本。
つる草模様の簡単な装飾。"	"Untitled. Looks like a cheap, handmade 
book with a simple decoration of grassy 
patterns."	"Sans titre. On dirait un livre ordinaire 
relié à la main et décoré de motifs 
bucoliques."	"Un volume senza titolo, dall'aspetto 
economico, fatto a mano, arricchito da 
una semplice decorazione che richiama 
l'erba."	"Ohne Titel. Mehr schlecht als recht 
von Hand gebunden. Mit schlichten 
Grasmustern verziert."	"Libro anónimo y de aspecto un tanto 
burdo adornado con unos ribetes 
sencillos."
151	ぽい感じの手作りの本。						
152	つる草模様の簡単な装飾。						
153	「たあへるあなとみあ」	"「たあへるあなとみあ」
人体の神秘があかされている。"	"""Cray's Anatomy"": Revealing the 
wonders of the human body.
 (Rated R.)"	"Tout ce que vous avez toujours voulu 
savoir sur le corps humain. 
Pour un public averti."	"In Carne e Ossa. Questo volume svela 
tutti i segreti del corpo umano. Adatto 
anche ai minori solo se assistiti da un 
adulto."	"„Anatomische Tabellen nebst 
dazugehörigen Anmerkungen.“ 
Überlässt nichts der Fantasie."	"«Anatomía de Cray». Incluye alguna que 
otra ilustración subidita de tono."
154	人体の神秘があかされている。						
155	　						
156	勇者３点セットの１つ。	"勇者３点セットの１つ。
真の勇者の証らしい。"	"One piece of the three-piece hero's 
collection. Said to prove the 
wearer is a true hero."	"Une des 3 pièces de la collection 
du héros. Son possesseur 
est un héros."	"Uno dei tre pezzi che 
compongono il kit eroico. Chi la 
indossa dimostra di essere un vero eroe."	"Aus dem 3-teiligen Heldenset. 
Zeichnet den Träger als wahren 
Helden aus."	"Una de las tres piezas del 
conjunto de héroe que demuestra 
la valía de su portador."
157	真の勇者の証らしい。						
158	　						
159	伝説の、なぞのアイテム。	"伝説の、なぞのアイテム。
時の壁をこえられると言われて
いるが。"	"A legendary item that is a complete 
enigma. It is believed to break the bonds 
of time."	"Objet légendaire qui demeure une 
énigme. Il briserait les liens du temps."	"Quest'oggetto leggendario è un vero 
mistero... Si dice che permetta di 
spezzare i confini del tempo."	"Ebenso legendär wie mysteriös. 
Man munkelt, es könne die Mauern der 
Zeit durchbrechen."	"Objeto legendario y sumamente 
enigmático. Dicen que es capaz de 
traspasar los límites del tiempo."
160	時の壁をこえられると言われて						
161	いるが。						
162	＃５４	<Missing>					
163	　だみー						
164	　　からデータ						
165	＃５５	<Missing>					
166	　だみー						
167	　　からデータ						
168	＃５６	<Missing>					
169	　だみー						
170	　　からデータ						
171	＃５７	<Missing>					
172	　だみー						
173	　　からデータ						
174	＃５８	<Missing>					
175	　だみー						
176	　　からデータ						
177	＃５９	<Missing>					
178	　だみー						
179	　　からデータ						
180	＃６０	<Missing>					
181	　だみー						
182	　　からデータ						
183	自分は戦闘に参加せず、仲間が	"自分は戦闘に参加せず、仲間が
代わりに戦ってくれる。"	"No need to participate in battles when 
friends can fight for you! "	"Pourquoi prendre part au combat quand 
des amis peuvent se battre pour vous ?! "	"Non c'è bisogno di prendere parte alle 
battaglie quando i tuoi amici possono 
combattere per te!"	"Warum dauernd selbst kämpfen, wenn 
man Gefährten hat, die für einen 
einspringen können? "	"¿Para qué luchar uno mismo cuando 
puedes pasarle el marrón a un amigo? "
184	代わりに戦ってくれる。						
185	　						
186	プレイスピードをコントロール	"プレイスピードをコントロール
{ButtonFast}      ：早送り
{ButtonSlow}      ：スロー再生"	"Controls the flow of time... 
{ButtonFast}      = Fast Forward 
{ButtonSlow}      = Slow Motion"	"Contrôle le passage du temps... 
{ButtonFast}      = Avance rapide
{ButtonSlow}      = Ralenti"	"Controlla lo scorrere del tempo. 
{ButtonFast}      = Avanzamento veloce 
{ButtonSlow}      = Avanzamento lento"	"Reguliert die Spielgeschwindigkeit. 
       Beschleunigen = {ButtonFast}
       Verlangsamen = {ButtonSlow}"	"Controla el paso del tiempo... 
{ButtonFast}      = cámara rápida
{ButtonSlow}      = cámara lenta"
187	　　　ボタン：早送り						
188	　　　ボタン：スロー再生						
189	たとえそこが地の果てでも、お	"たとえそこが地の果てでも、お
客がいれば飛んでいく。それが
鍛冶屋の職人としての意地だ。"	"Wherever there's a customer, 
a blacksmith will be there! 
Just summon the master smith's spirit..."	"Où qu'il y ait un client, le forgeron est 
présent ! Il suffit d'invoquer l'esprit d'un 
maître en la matière..."	"Ovunque c'è un cliente, c'è anche un 
fabbro! Basta evocare lo spirito del 
fabbro maestro..."	"Wo ein Auftrag ist, lässt kein Schmied 
lange auf sich warten! 
Beschwört den Meisterschmied."	"Un buen herrero nunca abandona a sus 
clientes. ¡No tienes más que invocarlo!"
190	客がいれば飛んでいく。それが						
191	鍛冶屋の職人としての意地だ。						
192	ダミーデータ	<Missing>					
193	ダミーデータ						
194	ダミーデータ						
